All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We're on דף Daf מ"ג Mem
Gimmel 43. We pick up on the bottom of מ"ב עמוד ב'.
Mem Bais amud Bais. Okay, all right, so again, מ"ג Mem Gimmel
43 but we pick up on the bottom of מ"ב עמוד ב'
Mem Bais amud Bais and אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק. Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak. I'm sorry, כי נח נפשיה. Ki nach nafshai. Four
lines from the bottom, end of the line. The משנה Mishna had
said that the משנה Mishna had said that only when people are
reclining
together to sit down to eat bread, one person may make המוציא
Hamotzi for
everybody and the problem was was that we had a ברייתא Braisa
that said even when they sit down, even when they don't recline
and the גמרא Gemara made a distinction which is if you said
"let's go eat bread over there," then that's considered being קובע, Koveia,
you're agreeing as a group, you're inviting, you're designating and therefore it's
like you're eating together as a group and one person can make
the ברכה Bracha for everybody. Again, whether it's the first ברכה Bracha
or the last ברכה, Bracha, whether המוציא Hamotzi or ברכת המזון, Birkas
hamazon, there's an idea that you constitute a group. However, if you
do not designate a place and you're sitting and not reclining, then
you're more like a bunch of individuals that got together and you
cannot make a ברכה Bracha for the group. And again, this points
out that the ריטב"א Ritva says it explicitly that ברכת הנהנין Birchas
hanehenin or ברכת המזון Birchas hamazon are not like other ברכות Brachos
that you could be יוצא Yotzei through somebody else. Here fundamentally the
idea is you're the one that experienced or is about to experience
the benefit, the pleasure, it's very subjective, it's very personal, you're the
one who has to make the ברכה, Bracha, you can't piggyback on
somebody else's ברכה. Bracha. The exception is when you're not doing it
as an individual but you're doing it as a member of a
group. Then the leader of the group, the person doing the זימון
Zimmun or the person here making the ברכה Bracha can represent the
group, but there it's not coming as an individual. So this only
works when you have הסיבה Haseiba or something equivalent to הסיבה Haseiba
which defines your eating as a group and not as a collection
of individuals.
So I just, is there any other dimension to it other
than it's a formal definition, that is to say the choreography of
the way we are seated is
defining the nature of the meal? It's independent still of my subjective
experience of satisfaction. In other words is there a degree of סמוכה
כגופה? Smucha ke-gufa? No. Is there a concept here that מה פתאום
Ma pitom that you could be יוצא Yotzei on a subjective experience
that you had by my reciting the ברכה?
Bracha? Right, so I think the point is is that we reframe,
yes, we are all experiencing the benefit personally, but it also reframes
it in one way to say it is you as a group
are also deriving pleasure. So we're sort of putting aside your personal
experience of pleasure and looking at you as a member of this
group that had this experience. So if you look at yourself as
a member of a group that had the experience then one person
can speak for the group.
So we're assuming that the הסיבה Haseiba in a way is indicating
the כוונה Kavana of every individual to see themselves as the members
of a group. It's a כוונה Kavana driven formulation.
Yes, but there are two possibilities and that's exactly what it says.
One way is the reality of הסיבה, Haseiba, maybe it gets at
כוונה, Kavana, maybe even without כוונה, Kavana, the social construct of הסיבה
Haseiba designates this as a group experience. And the other example was
you're just sitting but you said "let's all go have a meal
over there" and there it's very clearly your words and your כוונה.
Kavana. But there are ways in which it's framed as a group
experience and therefore we're not focusing on you as an individual, we're
focusing on the experience of a group and a person can represent
the group. Let me read a little bit more then I'll take
your question. So let's take a look, let's start reading. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: כי נח נפשיה, Ki nach nafshai, four lines
from the bottom, end of the line. כי נח נפשיה דרב, Ki
nach nafshai de-Rav, when רב Rav died, אזלו תלמידא בתריה, Azul tamidai
basrei, his students followed him, meaning followed his funeral bier, his coffin,
to bury him. כי הדרי, Ki hadari, when they were coming back
from the funeral, אמרי ניזיל וניכול לחמא אנהר דנק, Amri neizil ve-neichol
lachma a-nahar Dank, let's go over there to that river, to that
riverbank and go eat and go have break some bread, have a
meal. Okay, so they took out their sandwiches. They went over there
on their way back to the city. בתר דכרכי, Basar de-karchi, after
they sort of wrapped their bread, they ate their bread, יתבי וקמיבעיא
להו. Yasvi ve-ka mibaya lehu. They were sitting and they were asking,
they raised a question: הסיבה דוקא תנן, Haseiba davka tenan, aval יאשבו
לא? yashvu lo? Is it only when they recline, we're not reclining
here, we don't have our, you know, Roman couches that we're reclining,
we're sitting on a riverbank. So therefore one person cannot make for
the group. או דלמא, Od dilma, כיון דאמרי ניזיל וניכול ריפתא בדוכתא
פלוניא, Keivan de-amri neizil ve-neichol rifta beduchta peloniya, maybe if you say
"let's go eat bread in that place," כהסיבה דמי, Ke-haseiba dami, it's
like they reclined and we can make one person for the group.
So the resolution we said before here wasn't known to them and
they wanted to ask that question. What's the story if you don't,
if you sit but you designate a joint eating? So לא הוה
בידייהו, Lo havah beyadeihu, they didn't know what the answer was.
They should have asked their רבי Rebbe before he died.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. קם רב אדא
בר אבא, Kam Rav Adda bar Abba, top of מ"ג עמוד
א',
Mem Gimmel amud
Aleph, אהדר קריא לאחוריה. Ahadeir karei le-achorei. So they had all rent
their garments because they tore קריעה Kriya because if somebody's רבי מובהק
Rebbe muvshak dies, not only if a parent dies. So they... but
he felt this profound sense of loss again. So he took the
torn part of his garment, he turned it around, so now his
back was facing his front and vice versa. ואהדר קרעיה לאחוריה. Vahader
karei leachorei. So now he rent his garment again. The back which
was now in his front, he did another rending of the garment
because he felt the
need to ask a שאלה shaila and he couldn't.
Exactly. He felt once again what it meant that their רבי Rebbe
had died. אמר Amar he said, נח נפשיה דרב, Nach nafshei deRav,
רב Rav has passed away, וברכת מזונא לא גמרינן, u'virchas mazona lo
gamrinan, and we still don't even have learned from him how to
make blessings over the food. How is it? Look, he died and
we still haven't learned everything we need to learn from him. Maybe
even these most basic things. עד דאתא ההוא סבא, Ad de'asa hahu
saba, until a person, a certain elder came along, רמא להו מתניתין
אברייתא, rama lehu masnisin abraisah, and he said, wait one minute, look,
there's a problem. The משנה Mishnah contradicts the ברייתא. Braisah. The משנה
Mishnah says you have to do הסבה, haseiba, reclining. The ברייתא Braisah
says even sitting. ושני להו, Veshani lehu, and he answered them, here's
the way to resolve it. כיון דאמרי נזיל וניכול לחמא בדוך פלן
הסבה דמי. Keivan de'amri nazil venichol lachma beduch pelan haseiba dami. Once
you actually once you say let's go eat over there, it's like
הסבה haseiba and therefore I've solved your problem. Yes, even though you're
sitting and not reclining, it actually works out that the resolution of
the משנה Mishnah and ברייתא Braisah teaches you that that also counts
if you designate that place. So again, it's nice that they resolve
that issue. I don't know exactly how to unpack this from the
narrative sense. The fact that it's an anonymous person. Who is it?
That it's an anonymous person that's resolving it,
in a way it almost counterbalances that sense of loss, which is,
it's true it was a terrible thing you lost your רבי, Rebbe,
but on the other hand, there's a lot you can figure out
yourself. Even an anonymous person, if you work hard enough, you look
at the משנה, Mishnah, the ברייתא Braisah whatever, you can also come
to certain of these resolutions. You don't have to it's not all
dependent on what you learn from your רבי. Rebbe. So a little
bit undercutting the previous message. Not to minimize the loss of רב,
Rav, but maybe to emphasize, you're left to your own devices, you
can also figure things out. Yes, David.
With all due respect, it doesn't seem to say you can figure
it out yourself.
He figured it out for them.
Yes.
ההוא סבא, Hahu saba, probably a term for אליהו הנביא.
Eliyahu HaNavi. It seems to say that there's wisdom in the people.
Oh, you mean not even for you as students of רב. Rav.
It's an anonymous person. It suggests. Oh, that's interesting. Actually with the
people.
Well, that's an interesting. Thank you. I appreciate that. It's an interesting
counterpoint.
יישר כח. Yasher koach. Okay. Nice explanation.
I think Michael did you want to say something.
Is there any discussion or will we get to this later? But
as to how much time after you eat you have to do
this? Like make a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona or benching?
Yeah, yeah, we'll get to it. We're not up to ברכה אחרונה.
bracha achrona. That'll be next פרק.
perek. And also let's say you didn't really know like what you
ate but it filled you.
All right, whatever. All benching issues for next פרק. perek. Yes.
I know I was going to say that actually yes there is
those that say that every time it says ההוא סבא hahu saba
it means אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu HaNavi. So if you read it that
way, thank you, if you read it that way, then it's maybe
he sees they're so grieved that he needs to somehow make them
feel better so he comes and he helps them. But without reading
it as אליהו הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi, I do think it does serve
as a little counter-message to the loss of their רבי. Rebbe. I
like David's point that not only they have the wherewithal, but maybe
they have to really even hear what the people have to say.
Works for me. Okay, so not here on חולין. Chullin. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara continues. הסיבו אחד מברך. Heiseibu echad mevarech. Now when
they reclined, one person says the המוציא Hamotzi for everybody. This is
what we've been talking about. So the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, לא שנו אלא פת דבעי הסבה. lo shanu ela pas
debai haseiba. When is this? That when one person can make the
ברכה bracha for everybody? That's by bread. אבל יין לא בעי הסבה.
Aval yayin lo bai haseiba. For wine, that you could be considered
a group and one person could make בורא פרי הגפן borei peri
hagafen even without הסבה. haseiba. It sounds that way from the end
of the משנה Mishnah because the beginning of the משנה Mishnah talks
about bread and says הסיבו. heiseibu. The end of the משנה Mishnah
where we're talking about the wine after the meal and one person
saying for everybody, it does not mention הסבה. haseiba. It does not
mention הסבה. haseiba. So when it comes to wine, again presumably the
social conventions were such that it could be considered like a drinking
group. Like when we're all gone out to a bar and you're
sitting at a booth or something. It's not הסבה. haseiba. You drink
as a group without הסבה. haseiba. So you don't need הסבה haseiba
and therefore somebody can make it for the group.
Is there הסבה haseiba for a meal with the exception of the
סדר Seder on ליל פסח? Leil Pesach? Is there הסבה haseiba like
our sea...
Right. So we mentioned that yesterday when we did the משנה. Mishnah.
Exactly. No, it's fine. In this context of Roman culture, the way
they would eat the meal would be you recline on these couches,
beds, and you have this little table in front of you. So
if everybody is doing it, how do you eat a collective meal?
It's everybody doing הסבה. haseiba. If people are sitting on chairs, it's
more like
you come in, you leave, it's not really fixing your position there.
It's like you quickly sat by a cafeteria table, you had your
meal and you left. So but what it's saying is that's by
the basic food meal. By wine, you can drink together as a
group without הסבה. haseiba. So that's what רב Rav says. רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. אפילו יין נמי
בעי הסבה haseiba. *afilu yayin nami baei hiseiba*. No, it's not true.
To drink together as a group, it also is only in the
context of הסבה *hiseiba*. איכא *Ika*, that's one version whether wine needs
it. איכא דאמרי *Ika damri* others say, אמר amar רב Rav לא
lo, שנו אלא פת *Amar Rav lo shanu ela pas*, it's only
by bread דמהני ליה הסבה *demahane leh hiseiba* that הסבה *hiseiba* is
meaningful, meaning הסבה *hiseiba* defines it as a group experience. אבל יין
לא מהני ליה הסבה *Aval yayin lo mahane leh hiseiba*, it doesn't
help. Which seems to be that everybody agrees to the phenomenon that
they did not really do הסבה *hiseiba* as much as a fixed
sort of practice as they did when they had a gezitze, when
they had bread, when they had a meal. So what does that
mean if הסבה *hiseiba* is not so much part of drinking wine?
Does it mean that as wine you can see that it constitutes
a group without it? Or does it mean no, because it's not
so much a fixed part of it, even when you have it
it's not meaningful, that you're never seen as drinking as a group?
Again, the social reality or whatever your experience might be such, but
sort of in terms of a societal institution, that's only הסבה *hiseiba*
by bread. That defines a type of a group meal, nothing else
has that weight. So no, no, no, this is not... well, זימון
*zimun* we're not worrying about right now, but probably it's talking about
making an על הגפן *al hagefen* for the group, but we're talking
about the ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona *beracha rishona*. Okay, so this two
versions of what it means that הסבה *hiseiba* is not a staple
by wine. One is it's not needed and the other is it
doesn't even suffice. You can never really define the same type of
experience by wine. Okay, אבל יין לא מהני ליה הסבה *aval yayin
lo mahane leh hiseiba*. ורבי יוחנן אמר *VeRabbi Yochanan amar*, Rabbi Yochanan
says, אפילו יין נמי מהני ליה הסבה *afilu yayin nami mahane leh
hiseiba*. No, it can work. הסבה *hiseiba* also is meaningful for wine
even if it's not so much of a staple as it is
by bread. מיתיבי Meitivei, *Meitivei*, I'll ask you on this. כיצד סדר
הסבה *Keitzad seder hiseiba*. This is a תוספתא Tosefta. *Tosefta*. What is
the way they would do הסבה *hiseiba*? This is a very fascinating
תוספתא *Tosefta* because as you'll see, it's not all about הלכה halacha
*halacha*. This is really a תוספתא *Tosefta* that really is about sort
of just recording the normal social practice of how they would go
and eat their meal. דרך ארץ *Derech eretz*. But even and some
of it is even less even prescriptive, it seems almost just descriptive
about what was their normal practice. So let's take a look. כיצד
סדר הסבה *Keitzad seder hiseiba*? What was the way of הסבה *hiseiba*?
אורחין נכנסין ויושבין על גבי ספסל ועל גבי קתדראות *Orchin nichnasin veyoshvin
al gabi safsal ve'al gabi katedraot*. So the guests come in and
they sit on stools, on benches, or on קתדראות *katedraot*, cathedras, chairs.
Okay, which is what a קתדרא *katedra* means, it's a chair, okay,
Roman chairs. They would come in, you'd have them sit at the
bar. They wouldn't just come in recline down onto the couch. Okay,
עד שיכנסו כולם *ad sheyikanesu kulam*, until they wait until everybody gets
gathered together. הביאו להם מים *Heviu lahem mayim*, then they brought water.
כל אחד ואחד נוטל יד אחת *Kol echad ve'echad notel yad achat*.
Everybody would wash one hand. That would be their practice, they'd wash
one hand because we'll see they'll be holding the cup of wine
in that hand and that was seen to be the דרך ארץ
*derech eretz* what they would do. בא להם יין *Ba lahem yayin*,
then they were all served wine before the meal started. כל אחד
ואחד מברך לעצמו *Kol echad ve'echad mevarech le'atzmo*. Everyone makes his own
בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen, *Borei pri hagafen* because again they're
not reclining together, they're more seen as separate, etc. Okay, so they
each make a separate ברכה bracha, *beracha*. עלו והסבו *Alu vehisebu*, then
they went up into the main dining hall. So they're into a
different space. ובא להם מים *Uva lahem mayim*, so now you're going
to sit down for the bread. So you have to wash your
hands for bread. אף על פי שכל אחד ואחד נטל ידו אחת
*Af al pi shekol echad ve'echad notel yado achat*, even though each
one washed one hand for the wine, חוזר ונוטל שתי ידיו *chozer
venotel shtei yadav*. Now you go and you wash two hands. This
is for the הלכה halacha *halachic* requirement of washing hands for the
bread. The washing for the wine was just a practice.
This is the הלכה halacha *halachic* requirement of washing your hands before
bread. You can't wash one hand, wait a half hour, do the
other. Now you have to do both hands. בא להם יין *Ba
lahem yayin*, now they're having their meal. It's interesting because you would
have expected it now to say, notice it starts with כיצד סדר
הסבה *keitzad seder hiseiba*, what it's missing is now it should say
now they recline, they start eating their meal. It jumps over that,
went straight to the wine now. Now they're having their wine in
the middle of the meal. ובא להם יין *Uva lahem mayim*, now
they have more wine, אף על פי שכל אחד ואחד בירך לעצמו
*af al pi shekol echad ve'echad berach le'atzmo*, although everybody made a
ברכה bracha *beracha* for themselves, אחד מברך לכולן *echad mevarech lechulan*. You
have to make another ברכה bracha *beracha*, but here one can make
it for the group. Now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* completely sort
of skips over is that this contradicts the משנה Mishna *Mishna*. The
משנה Mishna *Mishna* says that if you make a ברכה bracha בורא
פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen *beracha Borei pri hagafen* before the meal,
it counts for the wine after and it sounds in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* it certainly counts for the wine during. Here why do
you have to make another ברכה bracha *beracha* during the meal if
you made בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen? *Borei pri hagafen* before?
So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, בא להם
יין *Ba lahem yayin*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, אף על גב דיין
שלפני המזון פוטר יין שלאחר המזון כל שכן זה שלפניו *Af al
gav deyayin shelifnei hamazon poter yayin shele'achar hamazon kol sheken zeh shelefanav*,
הוא שאני הכא כיון שעלו להסב הוי שינוי מקום וצריך לברך *hu
shani hacha keivan she'alu lehasev havei shinui makom vetzarich levarech*. When you
change your location it necessitates another ברכה bracha *beracha*. And this creates
a whole series of questions about שינוי מקום *shinui makom*, where you
make a ברכה bracha. *beracha* here and then you move to another
room, or you want to go, you know, you even go to
somebody else's house. Can you make קידוש kiddush, *Kiddush* in this room
and then go down to the social hall for the meal? And
what does it matter if you have it in mind? Does it
matter if it's under the same roof? So we're not going to
deal with that, but I wanted to at least alert you to
that. Why you're making another בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen *Borei
pri hagafen* according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is
that you're in an... In a different room, I think רש״י Rashi
says the same thing. Okay, so you're making another בורא פרי הגפן,
borei pri hagafen but here one person is making it for the
group. So that seems to be at least you can have an
idea of a group by wine. So the גמרא Gemara says, let's
take a look.
להך לישנא דאמר רב, L'hach lishna d'amar Rav, according to the version
that רב Rav says, לא שנו אלא פת דבעי הסיבה, lo shanu
ela pas d'ba'i haseiba, only bread requires הסיבה, haseiba, אבל יין לא
בעי הסיבה, aval yayin lo ba'i haseiba, wine does not require הסיבה.
haseiba. קשיא רישא, Kashya reisha, why in the case when you're having
your drinks before the meal is it individual? Why can't one person
make it for the group if you don't need הסיבה haseiba by
wine? גמרא Gemara says, שאני אורחין דדעתייהו למיעקר, shani urchin d'dataiyu l'me'akar,
no, guests are different because they're going to uproot themselves, they're going
to move themselves, which means what? It might be that they're going
to be moving to the other room, that's what רש״י says, that
they're not staying in this room. So this particular context where you
are serving drinks before the meal and going to move to another
room for the meal, everybody agrees in this context it's not seen
as being קובע koveia here for drinking. It's all very temporary, you're
having a little a drink or two while you're waiting for the
meal to be ready, it's not like you're sitting down as a
group to drink. So in this context it doesn't count. Otherwise though,
you wouldn't need הסיבה, haseiba, but in this context you're not drinking
as a group, it's not קובע מקום. koveia makom. That's how he
deals with that. ולהך לישנא דאמר רב, U'lhach lishna d'amar Rav, how
about the other version that he says only bread הסיבה haseiba works,
לא שנו אלא פת דמהני ליה הסיבה, lo shanu ela pas d'mahani
lei haseiba, אבל יין לא מהני ליה הסיבה, aval yayin lo mahani
lei haseiba, but wine הסיבה haseiba even הסיבה haseiba doesn't work and
you're always as individuals, you're never as a group? So קשיא סיפא,
kashya seifa, how do you explain the end where it says during
the meal one person can make the blessing for everybody? גמרא Gemara
says, no, שאני התם, shani hasam, there it's different, דמיגו דמהני ליה
הסיבה לפת מהני ליה הסיבה ליין, dimigo d'mahani lei haseiba l'pas mahani
lei haseiba l'yayin, since the הסיבה haseiba works for the bread, what
would we say that הסיבה haseiba doesn't work? The way I explained
it was, was there was no real type of social convention, or
certainly not as central of a convention of הסיבה haseiba by wine.
So it wasn't so meaningful by wine, so it was only a
meaningful thing by bread. So says, okay, that's if you all get
together to drink wine, there's no convention of הסיבה, haseiba, there's nothing
that defines this in a significant way as drinking together. But here
you're in the middle of the הסיבה haseiba for bread, you're in
this social convention of הסיבה haseiba for bread. So you're already defined
as eating your meal together. Since you're already defined from the eating
perspective as eating it together, even when you get around to the
drinking, the drinking has that context as well and you're also drinking
together.
So wine doesn't define the סעודה, seudah, it doesn't define eating together,
wine by itself according to this version, right? But that seems to
be the way, not because again, it seems to be because of
the nature of the convention of הסיבה haseiba was primarily by the
bread. Now the funny thing about this is that the משנה Mishna
says, if you look at the top line of the previous page,
בא להם יין בתוך המזון כל אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו לאחר המזון
אחד מברך לכולם, ba lahem yayin besoch hamazon kol echad v'echad mevarech
l'atzmo l'achar hamazon echad mevarech l'kulam, with exact opposite of the תוספתא.
Right, during the meal you make your own, and the גמרא Gemara
will get, the משנה Mishna will get the גמרא Gemara will get
to that in a minute, and after the meal it says one
can do for the group. Well, after the meal, what about if
we say הסיבה haseiba doesn't work for wine? Right? We were just
dealing with the opinion that says you can never have הסיבה haseiba
for wine. The only time one can make it for the group
is during the meal and our משנה Mishna. has you making בורא
פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen for drinking that's taking place after the
meal. In the ברכת המזון? Birkat Hamazon?
Maybe, I mean maybe it's after the meal, but it's still in
the context of the eating, it could be. It's interesting that the
גמרא Gemara does not try to bring this discussion in the context
of the משנה Mishna and therefore remains a little this whole issue
about when do we say there's this concept of הסיבה haseiba by
wine. Let's take a look, at least the גמרא Gemara now looks
at the next line in the משנה. Mishnah בא להם יין בתוך
המזון, ba lahem yayin besoch hamazon, you have the wine during the
meal, so there it says as opposed to the ברייתא Baraisa we
said before, one does it for the group, our משנה Mishnah said
during the meal everybody does it for themselves. So the גמרא Gemara
says, שאלו את בן זומא, sha'alu es Ben Zoma, they asked בן
זומא, Ben Zoma, מפני מה אמרו בא להם יין בתוך המזון כל
אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו? mipnei ma amru ba lahem yayin besoch hamazon
kol echad v'echad mevarech l'atzmo? If you remember, we had the same
type of they asked בן זומא Ben Zoma before, why if you
made המוציא Hamotzi do you have to make בורא פרי הגפן? Borei
Pri HaGafen So apparently בן זומא Ben Zoma was asked a lot
of questions about wine during a meal. So they said to him,
why during a meal can you have to make individually and one
person can't make for the group, ולאחר המזון אחד מברך לכולם, v'l'achar
hamazon echad mevarech l'kulam,
and afterwards one person can make for the group? אמר להם, Amar
lahem, he said to them, הואיל ואין בית הבליעה פנוי, ho'il v'ein
beis habli'ah panui, because your throat, your gullet is not empty. What
does that mean? So there's basically two explanations in the ראשונים. Rishonim.
One means if you allow somebody to lead the בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen during the meal, you're going to feel a need
to say אמן amen and you might be in the middle of
eating when he's saying his בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen and
then you'll choke on your food, so that's why not. Okay, so
therefore we wait and tell you to make your own ברכה, bracha
you'll make your own ברכה bracha when you're ready, but if somebody's
doing it for the group, you'll still be in the middle and
you'll say אמן amen and you'll say, and that won't be as
that'll be a little bit of a risky thing to say אמן
amen while somebody while you're in the middle of eating. The other
explanation is given is, is that if you're not if there's food
in your throat and you're not in a position where you are
fit to be drinking yourself, then it's not as meaningful that his
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen goes on you. experience if everybody
has like no food in their mouth, no food in their throat,
you make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen we all say
אמן Amen and then I go ahead and I drink, so the
fact that we it sort of brings us together in the experience
because we all could be drinking at this moment. But if I'm
eating while you're saying בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen I'm not
sort of a member a part of that experience part of that
group because right now with food in my mouth I can't be
drinking at this moment. Of course you'll say what are you talking
about I always do that I'm eating and I put some drink
down it helps wash the food down, but in time of the
גמרא Gemara they would not drink while they were at the same
time while they had food in their mouth while they were eating
and swallowing. Okay so it's interesting because the first explanation is like
a side issue, an important side issue but a side issue. We
don't want to do something that's risky. The other explanation gets back
to this idea that to make a בורא פרי הגפן borei pri
hagafen. for the group basically creates a group assumes or requires a
group experience. So even if somehow you're not eating right you're in
a position where you can't be drinking that undermines that sense of
it being a part of a group experience.
According to that let's say you know clink my glasses and
say אמן Amen make a toast so to speak so תוספות Tosafot's
asks a מקשה maksha question here what if about a case where
you don't have anything in your mouth? Maybe you should be allowed
and תוספות Tosafot basically says no they had like oh they made
basic rule they made basic they need the rule yes exactly they
objectified it after a point right and didn't go by case by
case. Anyway it does create a question nowadays under what circ how
do we you know how do we translate these social conventions which
aren't our reality to our cases? I already told you before that
תוספות Tosafot says תוספות's Tosafot. basic conclusion of all this סוגיא sugya
is that for us תוספות Tosafot speaking for him you know twelfth
thirteenth well thirteenth century actually one of the בעלי תוספות Ba'alei Tosafot
thirteenth century אשכנז Ashkenaz the only meaningful sort of group experience is
a with bread but it doesn't require הסבה. That's what תוספות Tosafot
said you know in translating it into his contemporary reality. What would
be the significance for our contemporary reality? That's another discussion. Again with
the נפקא מינא nafka mina about one person making a ברכה bracha
ראשונה for the whole group for other people. Okay now we go
on to a very different point.
יאחר המזון ye'acher hamazon does not mean the כוס של ברכה kos
shel bracha after ברכת המזון.
Birkat HaMazon. Correct יאחר המזון ye'acher hamazon is very clear the ראשונים
Rishonim say that explicitly it means a drinking they would do after
the food was removed and they would do some drinking before they
got around to בנטשן. benching. Okay so now the גמרא gemara goes
on והוא אומר על המוגמר. vehu omer al hamugmar. Now we get
to a very different point that the person there in the context
of the משנה mishna that which person makes for the group it
says the person that made the בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen
for the post-meal drinking also makes the ברכה bracha on the incense
that you burned after the meal for the group. So the same
person got one ברכה bracha got the other ברכה bracha and this
is going to lead us into a whole discussion about ברכה bracha
that you make on smell. Let's take a look. First the גמרא
gemara though deals with this convention of this convention
of who gets what who gets the
ברכה. bracha מדקתני והוא אומר על המוגמר midekatni vehu omer al hamugmar
since it says the guy that said the בורא פרי הגפן for
the group at the end also makes the ברכה bracha on the
incense והוא נטל ידיו תחילה vehu natal yadav techila I'm sorry that's
the line מכלל דאיכא עדיף מיניה michlal de'ika adif minei it sounds
like all things being equal I would have given it to somebody
else but because you did the בורא פרי הגפן you get to
do it on the incense. ואמאי ve'amai
why does he therefore get prefer you know precedence? הואיל והוא נטל
ידיו תחילה באחרונה ho'il vehu natal yadav techila beachrona since he was
the one that first washed his hands for the מים אחרונים mayim
achronim at the meal therefore he gets to do the first thing
after the meal which is the ברכה bracha. on the incense. It's
a little funny because the משנה Mishnah didn't mention מים אחרונים mayim
achronim at all. It mentioned making the ברכה bracha. on the wine
so this sort of assumes what is it facts not in evidence?
It assumes that since you made the ברכה bracha on the wine
you also get the honor or the convention was of you wash
your hands first for the מים אחרונים mayim achronim and since you're
going to wash your hands first for the מים אחרונים mayim achronim
therefore you're going to make the ברכה bracha on the incense. Maybe
you wash your hands first for the מים אחרונים mayim achronim because
as we saw before you people would wash their hands before holding
the glass of wine. So if you're going to be making the
ברכה bracha on the wine maybe anyway it's not clear but it
assumes that you washed also first for מים אחרונים mayim achronim and
somehow that explains why you are making the ברכה bracha on the
incense.
Didn't we learn yesterday that there's not supposed to be a הפסק
hefsek between the מים אחרונים mayim achronim and the ברכת המזון? Birkat
HaMazon?
Right so you wash your hands everybody washes their hands we start
with me I do it I pass it around the table then
we all do ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon. Oh the מוגמר mugmar is
after.
And the מוגמר mugmar is
after ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon right but somehow since somehow I made
the ברכה bracha first on our wine drinking and then there's a
convention presumably that I do the first thing after ברכת המזון Birkat
HaMazon and then the convention is that I do the first ברכה
bracha on the incense. מסייע ליה לרב mesayei lei leRav this supports
רב Rav, דאמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר רב de'amar Rav Chiyya
bar Ashi amar Rav הנוטל ידיו תחילה באחרונה hanotal yadav techila beachrona
the person who is first to do the מים אחרונים mayim achronim
הוא מזומן לברכה hu mezuman levracha he is the one that is
sort of designated in the batter's box for the ברכה. bracha, So
basically it's sort of like המתחיל במצוה אומרים לו גמור hamatchil bemitzvah
omrim lo gemor except this is not the same מצוה mitzvah but
somehow you know if this puts you in a position to next
thing. It's interesting in the convention we have nowadays also about the
person who does you know who does סליחות selichot the person who
does שחרית shacharit sometimes there's an assumption of things coming together although
there it's not necessarily one כיבוד kibbud you get another there's a
logical connection but סליחות selichot is a type of a תפילה. tefilla.
You know, it starts with אשרי, Ashrei, it has the whole part
in the middle, which is, you know, obviously the סליחות Selichos part
and the calling out to God, and then it ends with קדיש,
Kaddish, with קדיש תתקבל. Kaddish Tiskabel. So there there's a real sort
of a תפילה-like tefillah structure. Here somehow because you did מים אחרונים
mayim acharonim that entitles you to the next ברכה.
bracha, To the extent that people do מים אחרונים mayim acharonim should
they really give the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
to the person who has the מוגמר? mugmar? We don't do מוגמר.
mugmar. I know, but I mean who like will do ברכת המזון
birkas hamazon maybe? Okay, רב ורבי חייא, Rav v'Rabbi Chiya, רב ורבי
חייא הוו יתבי קמיה דרבי
בסעודתא Rav v'Rabbi Chiya hava yatvei kamey d'Rabbi b'seudata were sitting in
front of רבי, Rabbi, right, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, at
a meal. אמר ליה רבי לרב, Amar lei Rabbi l'Rav, so רבי
Rabbi said to רב, Rav קום משו ידך, kum meshu yadecha, go
wash your hands. So חזייה דהוה מרתת, chazyei d'hava mirtat, רב Rav,
was very sort of like fearful. Go wash my hands? What? He
thought I came with dirty hands to the table? He saw he
saw I had something on my hands? Go wash your hands! So
אמר it's like what I mean talk to my kids. Did you
wash your hands? Right? Go wash your hands first. אמר ליה רבי
חייא, Amar lei Rabbi Chiya, so anyway, so אמר ליה רבי חייא
amar lei Rabbi Chiya said to רב, בר פחתי bar pachti which
is a whole question what that means, if it's a compliment or
an insult, but anyway, let's say it means, you know, important
one, איינא דברכת מזונא קאמר לך. ayeina d'birkas mazona ka'amar lach.
What he's telling you to wash your hands is he wants to
give you the honor of making ברכת המזון, birkas hamazon, of leading
the benching, so therefore he said you should wash your hands first.
So here's the sort of point that Michael made, not the ברכה
bracha on the מוגמר mugmar but the idea of washing the hands
leading to the ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. So somehow while our משנה
talks about the ברכה bracha on the wine leading to the מוגמר,
mugmar, the גמרא gemara talks about it about the washing of the
hands leading leading going to leading the ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and
maybe and that also therefore when they had the this מוגמר mugmar
leading to the מוגמר. mugmar. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara turns its
attention from all this question about group and leading the group to
this issue about ברכה bracha. on on smells. Let's take a look.
אמר רבי זירא אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav, so רבי
זירא בר ירמיה, Rabbi Zeira bar Yirmiya, מאימתי מברכין על הריח? me'eimasai
mevorchin al hare'ach? When do you make a ברכה bracha. on smell,
meaning the smell of burning incense? משתעלה תימרתו, mishetaleh timraso, from when
the column of smoke rises up.
Okay,
let's go back to that after we see the next discussion and
figure out what that's about. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרב בר ירמיה,
Amar lei Rabbi Zeira l'Rav bar Yirmiya, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said to the same רב בר ירמיה, Rav bar Yirmiya, והא לא
קא ארח? v'ha lo ka arach? What do you mean when the
pillar of smoke goes up? You haven't yet smelled it.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, ולטעמיך u'leta'amecha according to you, המוציא לחם מן
הארץ מברך, hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz mevarech, you make the ברכה bracha
of המוציא לחם מן הארץ, hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz, והא לא אכל?
v'ha lo achal? You haven't eaten it. אלא דעתיה למיכל, Ela da'atei
l'meichal, you're planning on eating it. הכא נמי דעתיה לארוחי, Hacha nami
da'atei l'oruchei, here too you're planning on smelling it. Now, it's such
an obvious exchange, what's going on? And what we are going to
see, I mean the גמרא Gemara is going to say this, but
I am going to tell you that the implicit subtext here is
how much is the blessing on smell like a ברכת הנהנין, birchas
hanehenin, like deriving benefit like from food and drink, and how much
is it like a ברכת השבח? birchas hashevach? You see something beautiful
and you give praise to God for the beautiful thing that you've
experienced. The difference is is that a ברכת הנהנין birchas hanehenin you
make before you get the הנאה. hana'ah. It's basically saying I do
not I'm not entitled to this benefit, I have to give this
praise, give this acknowledgment and then I can derive the benefit. אסור
לאדם ליהנות מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה. assur l'adam lehenos min ha'olam
hazeh belo bracha. A ברכת השבח birchas hashevach is doesn't it's focus
you know it's like you're walking and you see beautiful trees, you
see a rainbow, you have some experience and you praise God and
you give שבח, shevach, but it's not to allow the allow you
to derive that benefit. So that seems to be the question here
because you know obviously the benefit of smell is not the same
as the benefit of taste of eating, of filling your stomach, of
your taste buds, it's not the same degree. Think for a minute
how about the benefit of sight? When you see something aesthetically beautiful,
right, we see something that from the vision is meaningful, again the
rainbow, a blossoming tree, that's a ברכה bracha. of שבח. shevach. We
don't say oh I can't see until I make the ברכה, bracha
now I can now I can move my hand away from eyes
and get the ברכה, bracha? it's a ברכה bracha of שבח. shevach.
But
so here too, why oh I can't smell before? No, maybe it's
not about eating and food, it's more about שבח shevach and not
about a ברכה bracha to allow the benefit. So therefore so therefore
the first side is, you know, you got to smell it first.
It's not like food. You have to smell it only after you've
experienced it, only after you see the trees, you see the rainbows
you make the ברכה. bracha And his answer back is no, I
treat it like המוציא Hamotzi and before you even can derive the
benefit I'm going to make a ברכה. bracha. And that might be
why he said that you need the pillar to go up because
because smoke is different than sight, that at least in the case
of incense, would it be true I mean smoke smell, at least
in case of incense, not necessarily the other smells, there's a thing
there, there's the pillar of smoke, there's the aroma, so it's more
thingy, it's more like an object, so there could be a vision
right right but it's more like there's some substance to it, you
can say I'm going to bring this smell into my body, it's
like food, I have to make a ברכה bracha before I can
bring it into my body, whereas the other experience was it's not
like food, first you get the experience like first you see the
thing and then you make the ברכה. bracha.
But it's still הנהנין hanehenin to the extent that you know even
for שבח shevach and I can just make it when
I...
No, because you
can't, because it's not about seeing; here the שבח shevach is on
the smell experience, the same way in other cases the שבח shevach
is on the sight experience.
Well, I know it's going to smell good,
I don't have to smell it. No, if I smell a new
tree without seeing a new tree... here the שבח shevach is on
the way you experience it was through smell, as opposed to the
other thing, you experience things through sight.
No, but why I
don't know why you're assuming that here the sight experience is a
significant enough experience.
No, there's a tremendous נפקא מינא nafka mina as well, so in
other words, if it's a matter of הנאה, hana'ah, then if I'm
deriving benefit from smelling something which is forbidden, then I shouldn't make
that blessing, whereas if it's a matter of שבח, shevach, that wouldn't
be an issue. Like if I walk by a restaurant and it
smells phenomenal and it's all
איסור. issur.
Well, I hope it's not בשר בחלב basar b'chalav because that's אסור
בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah.
No, but
if it's a matter of שבח, shevach, if it's a matter of
שבח, shevach, you still maybe should make the ברכה bracha despite the
problem of איסור.
issur. That's an interesting question.
Yeah, but what about perfume?
So we'll get to that. We'll see what the different ברכות. brachos.
Let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. By the way,
about this issue about הנאה hana'ah or שבח, shevach, here's a mistake
that almost everybody makes: מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbat, בורא מאורי האש, Borei
Meorei Ha-Esh, do you look at your fingernails before or after you
make the ברכה? bracha Both. Right, most people, what do they do?
They
make the ברכה bracha first and then you do it, except that
there's no ברכת הנהנה birkat ha-nehenin of seeing a torch.
It's a ברכה bracha of שבח shevach
of בורא מאורי האש, Borei Meorei Ha-Esh, and the גמרא Gemara, actually
says, the משנה says, אין מברכין עד שיאותו לאור, ein mevorchin ad
she-ye-otu le-oro, until you derive benefit. Don't make the ברכה bracha until
you derive benefit. So really what you do is you look at
it and then
you make the ברכה. bracha. It's not a ברכת הנהנה, birkat ha-nehenin,
it's a ברכת שבח. birkat shevach. So I used to do that
and then I would sort of make a point, look at it
and then not look while the ברכה bracha, is being made and
then everybody would think it's weird, so I just keep on looking
at it but I start before I make the ברכה. bracha Okay,
so now let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara. says.
So this seems to be the base. אמר רבי חייא בריה דרבה
בר נחמני אמר רב חסדא אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר רב חסדא
אמר זעירי, Amar Rabi Chiya brei de-Rabba bar Nachmani amar Rav Chisda
amar Rav ve-amrei lah amar Rav Chisda amar Zeiri, question as to
who said this, but now we get to what ברכה bracha do
you make on which type of aromas. כל המוגמרות מברכין עליהן בורא
עצי בשמים, Kol ha-mugmarot mevorchin aleihen Borei Atzei Besamim,
all types of incense, the ברכה bracha is—because now what's the ברכה—בורא
עצי בשמים, Atzei Besamim wood—aromatic woods—חוץ ממוסק, chutz mi-musk, musk,
animal musk, which was made, it used to apparently in the old
times was made from certain glands, but certainly but רש"י Rashi already
says it was used from various extracts of certain animal excrement. That
should be מן חיה, min chaya, that doesn't come from plants, that
comes from animals, שמברכין עליו בורא מיני בשמים. she-mevorchin alav Borei Minei
Besamim. בורא מיני בשמים Borei Minei Besamim is like the שהכל she-hakol
of בשמים, besamim, okay? So just types of בשמים. besamim. So going
to your question, Bobby, about perfume, presumably it would be בורא מיני
בשמים. Borei Minei Besamim. מיתיבי, says the גמרא, Gemara I'll ask you
on this: אין מברכין בורא
עצי בשמים אלא על אפרסמון, Ein mevorchin Borei Atzei Besamim ela al
afarsamon, you only make the
ברכה bracha. of עצי בשמים atzei besamim, on אפרסמון, afarsamon, balsam, ושל
בית רבי ושל בית קיסר, ve-shel beit Rebbe ve-shel beit Keisar, on
the balsam of the house of Rebbe and on the balsam of
the house of the Caesar. Why the house of Rebbe, the house
of Caesar? So רש"י says it was particularly good, but again here
we go with Steinsaltz to the rescue. Balsam was so valuable as
a source of this, you know, sort of perfume and aromatic sort
of scent in the ancient times that number one he says it
was worth its weight in gold, which is fascinating. Charlie used to
tell us about certain spices that was worth its weight... saffron still
is. Saffron still is.
Really, still is.
Anyway, and that בית רבי—that beit Rebbe the kings and emperors or
whatever would have, you know, they would basically have private ownership over
like balsam orchards, like they were royal orchards, they really had to
like, you know, that it was under royal control it was so
valuable at the
time.
Presumably,
right.
Only the balsam grove... what?
Not the balsam fir we have in America. Okay, so only on
that, וההדס בכל מקום, ve-ha-hadas be-chol makom, and on הדס hadas everywhere.
That only there you make עצי בשמים, atzei besamim nothing else. Now
what's the distinction? One distinction might be that other types of things
are not aromatic enough, are not seen as fundamentally for their aroma
as these. Only these are primarily for their aroma. The other possibility
might be that you only make the ברכה bracha עצי בשמים atzei
besamim if the thing is בעין, be-ayin, it's a thing in front
of you, but when you're burning incense, you can't make עצי בשמים
atzei besamim. because it's no longer an עץ, etz, it's been burnt.
So that could be the other problem. So how can you say
you make בורא עצי בשמים Borei Atzei Besamim, on all types of
burnt incense? Here it says only these things. So it says תיובתא.
tiyuvta. All right, that's a contradiction. Now look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות
Tosafot says וההדס שבכל מקום, ve-ha-hadas she-be-chol makom, בעל הלכות גדולות, Ba'al
Halachot Gedolot, לא גריס תיובתא. lo garis tiyuvta.
He doesn't have the תיובתא, tiyuvta, which basically rejects the assertion, okay,
ומיישב... u-me-yashev... ומשני, umeshanei, and he has a different version of the
גמרא. Gemara. תנא הדס וכל דדמי ליה. tana hadas vechol didami lei.
Don't get so worked up. Yeah, it says myrtle, but it means
really anything, any type of aromatic plant you make בורא עצי בשמים.
Borei Atzei Besamim כל שעיקרו לריח, kol she'ikaro lareiach,
but it means that a type of a plant that is fundamentally
there to, not fundamentally if you want the, but the normal purpose
it serves is that it is that it gives off the smell.
לאפוקי תפוחים וחבושים שאין עיקרם לריח אלא לאכילה. la'apukei tapuchim vechavushim she'ein
ikaram lareiach ela la'achilah. Okay,
as opposed to other types of things which are not fundamentally, although
they might have a beautiful smell, the society mostly is interested in
them because of their food. So those things you do not make
בורא עצי בשמים. borei atzei besamim. בורא עצי בשמים borei atzei besamim.
is number one, something that grows and is עץ. etz. We'll see
what happens if it doesn't have the עץ etz quality. And number
two is primarily under, you know, its primary function in society is
as a source of smell, not as something else. Okay, and presumably
also even if it's being not בעין, be'ayin, if it's not in
its physical state, if it's being burnt and it's incense, you would
still make the same ברכה. bracha So given that, let's see how
תוספות ends this. ומי שהולך לבית שיש שם בשמים, umi sheholech leveit
sheyesh sham besamim, you're in a house that there's a lot of
spices around, ויש שם מיני בשמים שמריח בהם, veyesh sham minei besamim
shemeriach bahem, and he has all different types, ומספקא ליה אי ממין
עץ ממין אדמה הוא, umesapka lei ei mimi etz mimi adamah hu,
do you make בורא עצי בשמים borei atzei besamim or maybe it's
not an עץ, etz, maybe that's another type, it's a plant and
it's another ברכה, bracha. we'll see what that other ברכה bracha is
in a minute. So what ברכה bracha do you make? And look
at this: יש מפרשים שמברך שהכל נהיה בדברו, yesh mefarshim shemevarech shehakol
niheyah bidvaro, דעל כולם אם בירך שהכל יצא. de'al kulam im berach
shehakol yatza.
So he actually thinks that maybe you make a שהכל shehakol if
you don't know what ברכת בשמים birchat besamim to make. ורב רבינו
משה הוא היה אומר שיברך בורא מיני בשמים. verav Rabbeinu Moshe hu
hayah omer sheyevarech borei minei besamim.
So here there's a question where the גמרא Gemara, before said בורא
מיני בשמים, borei minei besamim, is it meant as a generic? תוספות
thinks it might be there's a generic of שהכל. shehakol. Which again
shows that תוספות really considers this to be fully in the ברכות
הנהנין birchot hanehenin category to the point that he thinks it's possible
you make a שהכל. shehakol. Now I should say we do פוסקין
pasken that it is in the ברכות הנהנין birchot hanehenin category. We
do פוסקין pasken that first you make the ברכה bracha. and then
you smell it. Okay, but that does seem to be at least
one of the questions that's going on here. Let's get back to
the גמרא.
Gemara Over of אפרסמון afarsamon as well, right? You make.
Yeah, but that's a different ברכה. bracha? It's a different. Okay, yes.
Isn't that an interruption?
All right, let's. Continue, please? אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב יצחק, amar
lei Rav Chisda leRav Yitzchak, אמר
ליה רב חסדא לרב יצחק. amar lei Rav Chisda leRav Yitzchak. האי
משחא דאפרסמון, hai mishcha de'afarsamon, how about oil of balsam oil? מאי
מברכין עילויה? mai mevorchin ileiveih? What ברכה bracha. do you make? There's
some taps of an assumption that you would get a special ברכה
bracha, because it was so valuable. Oil, balsam oil. So, אמר ליה
הכי אמר רב יהודה, amar lei hachi amar Rav Yehuda, this is
where רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said: בורא שמן ארצנו. borei shemen artzeinu. You create the oil of
our land of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Apparently, the balsam oil that
they had from יריחו Yericho was extremely valuable and a, like, you
know, big export of Israel. So anyway, בורא שמן ארצנו. borei shemen
artzeinu. I don't know export, I made that up. אמר ליה בר
מיניה דרב יהודה, amar lei bar mineih deRav Yehuda, eh, don't bring
proofs from רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דחביבא ליה ארץ ישראל. dechaviva lei
Eretz Yisrael. He loves Israel and he's going to look for an
opportunity to introduce that into a ברכה. bracha, אבל לכולי עלמא מאי?
aval lechuli alma mai? Everybody else, who okay, we also love Israel,
but we're not as crazy about it as he does, what ברכה
bracha. should they make? Okay? אמר ליה הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar
lei hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, this is where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says: בורא שמן ערב. borei shemen areiv. That you make very aromatic,
you know, pleasing oil. So there was a special ברכה bracha they
had just for this balsam oil. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar
Rav Adda bar Ahava, so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava says: האי קושטא מברכין עילויה בורא עצי בשמים. hai kushta mevorchin
ileiveih borei atzei besamim. This קושטא kushta you make בורא עצי בשמים.
borei atzei besamim Even Steinsaltz gave some word for it, but he
did not give a picture, I think. What does Steinsaltz say? Some
type of spice. He says
costus.
Costus, now you know.
Okay, אבל משחא כבישא לא. aval mishcha kevisha lo. But if you
just happen to be sort of immersed, pickled in oil, so that
it gives off the smell into oil, they would put this, they
put different aromatic plants into, you know, oil, and then the oil
would absorb the aroma. So in that case, you don't make a
ברכה. bracha Why? Because then it's not בעין. be'ayin. So maybe this
gets back to the case about the incense. Incense at least you
would put the incense in, it would be in its natural state,
and then you would experience it as it was burning. But how
about something that left its aroma somewhere else, like nowadays our perfumes,
and there is nothing physical of the original thing present? Do you
still make the ברכה? berucha So this first says: no, if all
you've got is the, is the smell that has been absorbed by
the oil, you don't make the ברכה.
berucha I mean essence, the essence
of it, and maybe you don't make any ברכה, berucha right? Okay,
or maybe at least you don't בורא עצי בשמים. borei atzei besamim.
רב כהנא אמר אפילו משחא כבישא. Rav Kahana amar afilu mishcha kevisha.
No,
even by the oil you would make the ברכה, בורא עצי בשמים.
borei atzei besamim.
אבל משחא טחינא, aval mishcha tchina, if it's sort of ground up
into the oil, where it doesn't presumably, you know, you know this,
right? Like sometimes if you chop something up, like if you mince
garlic rather than press garlic, it doesn't get the smell out as
well, right? So if you like chop the spice up and mix
it in the oil, it's not going to have the same smell
as if you really like have it soak in the oil and
the, and the aroma absorbed. So if it's just chopped up and
mixed in, לא, then it's not significant enough and on the one
hand. On the one hand you have more of the thing itself,
it's chopped up and it's in little pieces, but on the other
hand the smell is not so powerful and therefore it somehow does
not warrant the ברכה. נהרדעי אמרי Nehardei amrei נהרדעי Nehardei says אפילו
משחא דכביש ביה afilu misha dechavish bei even the oil that is
ground up in it. Okay. And then we've got a whole series
of questions about when is the thing primarily considered to be in
an enough of its state that it gets the ברכה of עצי
בשמים. atzei besamim? Now there is also questions about does everything warrant
עצי בשמים? atzei besamim. Not everything is an עץ. etz. So we
already had that mush you make a בורא מיני בשמים. borei minei
besamim. Let's see the other, other types of things. אמר רב גידל
אמר רב Amar Rav Giddel amar Rav
האי סמלוכ מברכין עלוי בורא עצי בשמים. hai samlok mevorchin alei borei
atzei besamim. This סמלוכ samlok you make עצי בשמים. atzei besamim. I
forget what he says סמלוכ samlok is. Jasmine. Oh right, Rashi says
it. Look at the first Rashi: יסמין. Yasmine.
Okay. Jasmine you make עצי בשמים. atzei besamim. אמר רב חנינא אמר
רב
Amar
Rav Chanina
amar Rav הני
חלפי דימא hanei chalfai deyama certain types of things that grow by
the sea, by the ocean. Again, what does he say this is?
Spikenard. Spikenard that grow by the ocean. I got a picture of
these. Anyway, מברכין עלוי בורא עצי בשמים. mevorchin alei borei atzei besamim.
You make עצי בשמים. atzei besamim, Now the חידוש chiddush here is
that these things are not necessarily trees, at least the second one.
I don't know what the, I don't know, what's jasmine? Does jasmine
grow on a tree? Anybody know?
It's like a plant. Yeah, well, like a bush.
It must be perennial.
Maybe. Anyway, so the question here is what constitutes a tree. So
at least in this case of these spikenard, אמר מר זוטרא amar
Mar Zutra מאי קרא mai kra where do you see from a
פסוק pasuk that if it grows on a stalk, even if it
doesn't grow from a tree, we can consider it a tree? ותעלם
הגגה ותטמנם בפשתי העץ. Vatialiha al hagag vatimnem befishtei ha’etz. And she
brought them up, right, by Rachav to the
roof, and she buried them in the flax stalks. So stalk here
is called עץ. etz. So therefore, things that grow on stalks you
could say עצי בשמים, atzei besamim. which is interesting. You would not
make a בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha’etz for eating fruit, right,
if there were fruit that would grow off a stalk. I mean,
barley you don't make בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha’etz, or wheat,
you say אדמה. adamah. There we said the definition of tree there
was something that lasts from year to year. Here, for whatever reason
by בשמים, besamim, they had a broader definition, and even things that
grow on stalks is עצי בשמים.
atzei besamim, Rachav was a מומחה mumcheh in perfume.
There you go.
Okay. האי נרקום דגניתא. Hai narkum deganisa.
This נרקום narkum of the garden. Remind me what he says נרקום
narkum is. I looked this all up last night. Bobby, what does
he say the next thing is?
Oh right, lily.
The lilies? Daffodil. Oh, daffodil. נרקיס. Narkis. Okay, fine. So a garden
daffodil, מברכין עלוי בורא עצי בשמים. mevorchin alei borei atzei besamim. The
wood of the בשמים besamim woods. דדברא De’davra of the field, בורא
עשבי בשמים, borei ispei besamim, the grasses of the בשמים. besamim. Now
I have no idea why those two daffodils are different. Steinsaltz was
not helpful here.
And are they?
Okay, but apparently they still would be used for smell.
They might, they grow from bulbs like onions, they come back.
Right. So I have no idea. I mean, here becomes, this is
a great way to test what is the difference, where do you
draw the line, what still falls in the category of עצי בשמים,
atzei besamim? what does it become עשבי בשמים. ispei besamim. It would
be nice to know what the difference is between garden daffodils and
field daffodils. So I don't know. It's not the same value. Garden
daffodil is עצי, atzei, field daffodil is עשבי. ispei. I don't really
know what the difference is, what you need to constitute עץ etz
for the purposes of this סוגיא. sugya.
Is one cultivated and one wild?
Well, that's certainly true. דדברא De’davra is wild, right,
and the גן gan is cultivated.
But why does that mean the difference between עץ etz and עשב?
esev? עשבי בשמים Ispei besamim is something you would make basically like
on flowers, right? It's things that grow that have smells but are
not sort of from, you know, are not like from trees. But
trees is a very broad definition here, right? Because right, how about
a rosebush, right? Roses are, I mean that has a hard vine
or whatever. You know, where exactly do you find עצי בשמים? atzei
besamim, I mean daffodils for God's sakes. So it's hard to see
exactly what the line is. אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet הני
סיגלי hanei siglei these סיגלי siglei which are violets.
Violets, thank you. Oh, violets, if you look at Rashi. Anyway, מברכין
עלוי בורא
עשבי בשמים. mevorchin alei borei ispei besamim. There you get a straight
flower you make בורא עשבי בשמים. borei ispei besamim. אמר מר זוטרא
Amar Mar Zutra האי מאן דמורח באתרוגא או בחבושא hai man demoreich
be’esroga o bechabusha if somebody smells an אתרוג esrog or a quince,
so this is something that is a smell from fruit, and the
fruit is primarily about
eating, אומר ברוך שנתן ריח טוב בפירות. omer baruch shenatan reiach tov
baperot. You say that you give a good smell to fruit. Presumably
maybe the reason it gave the example of an אתרוג esrog was
because, well, maybe it was just common to have, it has a
very nice aroma smell. But maybe also because you don't even eat
it raw. So maybe if you don't eat something raw, you might
think that maybe it's עצי בשמים, it's not so much of an
emphasis on fruit. No, it's still fundamentally a fruit, and therefore the
ברכה is that you give good aroma to fruit. It's not fundamentally
a type of a, you know, of an aromatic thing, it's fundamentally
a fruit.
Wait, can I ask a question?
Let's go a little further. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda האי
מאן דנפיק ביומי ניסן. hai man denafik beyomei Nisan. Now look at
this sort of, you know, seamless transition from ברכות brachot on smell
to seeing. ...new things and making ברכות *brachot* on blossoming trees. If
you go out in ניסן *Nissan* in the spring וחזי אילני דקא
מלבלבי *ve-chazi ilanei de-ka-melavlavei* and you see trees that are blossoming אומר
*omer* you say ברוך *Baruch* meaning ברוך אתה יי אלוהינו מלך העולם
*Baruch Atah Adonai Eloheinu Melech HaOlam* it just doesn't have the middle
part ברוך שלא חיסר בעולמו כלום *Baruch shelo chisar be-olamo klum* that
nothing is lacking in God's world וברא בו בריות טובות ואילנות טובים
*u-vara bo beriyot tovot ve-ilanot tovim* God made in it beautiful good
creations and good trees להתנאות בהם בני אדם *le-hitna'ot bahem benei adam*
that we as human beings can take pleasure in them. Okay now
what's interesting about this is okay first of all it transitions from
the smell the ברכה *bracha* mentions להתנאות *le-hitna'ot* to derive benefit which
makes us think of ברכת הנהנין *birchat ha-nehenin* but you make it
after you see it right? So again when what types of things
do you have to make a ברכה *bracha* in order to derive
benefit before what types of things after the experience of deriving pleasure
and benefit does it therefore motivate a ברכת השבח *birchat ha-shevach*?
You're not going to know until you see it whether or not
it's really maybe maybe.
אמר רב זוטרא *Amar Rav Zutra* the ברכה *bracha* is not limited
to
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.
No correct. Go ahead you look in your normal סידור *siddur* it's
there. Correct. אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב *Amar Rav Zutra
bar Tuvia amar Rav* said Rav Zutra bar Tuvia in the name
of Rav מנין שמברכין על הריח *minayin she-mevarchin al ha-reiach* how do
you know you make a ברכה *bracha* on smell? שנאמר כל הנשמה
תהלל יה *shene'emar kol ha-neshama tehalel Yah* as it is said all
souls will praise God איזו דבר שהנשמה נהנית ממנו ואין הגוף נהנה
ממנו *eizu davar she-ha-neshama nehenit mimenu ve-ein ha-guf nehena mimenu* what's something
that the soul gets benefit and not your body? Obviously we know
that smell is receptors in the body but nevertheless it's not the
same type of sustaining the body it feels like it's sort of
you as a person. הוי אומר זה הריח *havei omer zeh ha-reiach*
gets the smell. Now of course it's interesting because if I would
say how do you know you have to make a ברכה *bracha*
for smell it's because אסור להנות מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה *asur
l'henot min ha-olam ha-zeh b'lo bracha* right? You don't derive benefit without
a ברכה *bracha*. It's not what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. The
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says a separate פסוק *pasuk* which again indicates that
this is maybe has closer to a ברכת השבח *birchat ha-shevach* or
it's somewhat problematic to put it fully in the ברכת הנהנין *birchat
ha-nehenin* category. And that's underscored by the פסוק *pasuk*. The פסוק *pasuk*
says אין הגוף נהנה ממנו *ein ha-guf nehena mimenu*. It's not like
normal הנאה *hana'ah*. The same way you don't make a ברכת הנהנין
*birchat ha-nehenin* before sight because it's not about bodily pleasure it's aesthetic
it's emotional whatever it is so maybe you don't make it maybe
also smell is also אין הגוף נהנה ממנו *ein ha-guf nehena mimenu*.
So this seems to go be the back and forth dialectic going
on here about to what degree is smell like seeing things and
a ברכת השבח *birchat ha-shevach* and not הנאה *hana'ah*? You derive benefit
but it's not the same הנאה *hana'ah* or to what degree is
it in the classic הנאה *hana'ah* category? Let's get to the next
דף *daf*. ואמר רב זוטרא בריה דרב טוביה אמר רב *Ve-amar Rav
Zutra brei de-Rav Tuvia amar Rav* and also the same amora said
עתידים בחורי ישראל שיתנו טעם ריח טוב כלבנון *atidim bachurei Yisrael she-yitnu
ta'am reiach tov ke-Levanon* the young men of Israel will in the
future give off as beautiful an aroma as the Lebanon's forest. שנאמר
*shene'emar* no sounds like he means literally ילכו יונקותיו ויהי כזית הודו
וריח לו כלבנון *yelechu yonkotav ve-yehi che-zayit hodo
ve-reiach lo ke-Levanon* the branches will spread and will be like the
olive tree
and the smell will be like that of the Lebanon. And the
side has a different גירסא *girsa* which means that those that have
never sinned will have this so maybe it's more of a metaphysical
state. Okay now because we had Rav Zutra bar Tuvia we continue.
ואמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב *Va-amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia
amar Rav* מאי דכתיב *mai de-chtiv* what's meant by the פסוק *pasuk*
את הכל עשה יפה בעתו *et ha-kol asah yafeh be-ito*? Now we're
on a little אגדתא *agadeta* digression. Everything God did He did in
its right time proper. מלמד שכל אחד ואחד ייפה לו הקדוש ברוך
הוא אומנתו *melamed she-kol echad ve-echad yifeh lo ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu umanato*.
Every person God made every person's trade or profession beautiful in his
own eyes in the eyes of the
professional of that person. בשינתו *bi-shnato* at least for him. אמר רב
פפא Rav Pappa *Amar Rav Papa* היינו דאמרי אינשי *hainu d'amri inshi*
I don't know where he gets the word בשינתו *bi-shnato* but somehow
בשינתו *bi-shnato* עתו *ito* seems to be by some type of pun
word. אמר רב פפא Rav Pappa היינו דאמרי אינשי *Amar Rav Papa
hainu d'amri inshi* that's why people say תלי ליה קורא לדבר אחר
*tali lei kora l'dvar acher* if you hang a heart of palm
in front of a pig ואיהו עביד עובדיה *ve-ihu avid ovdei* and
he'll do his own thing he'll take that heart of palm and
he'll roll it in the mud. So for you it's like oh
my God what a waste of a beautiful thing to eat but
that's the way he likes things he likes it in the mud.
So everybody you look at somebody else's job and you say I
can't believe that this is the type of job you do I
would be disgusted if I would have to do that and that
person loves what they're doing and would feel turned off by what
you're doing. Now הלוואי *halevai* that that should always be true. A
lot of people are stuck in jobs that they
hate. But anyway but it does speak to the idea
that different that when we're committed to something maybe we actually learn
to define pleasure in it and so on and also that you
cannot judge other people's tastes and the things that other people sort
of are attracted to and invested in. Okay תא שמע ta shma
*Ta shema* so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. ואמר רב זוטרא *Ve-amar
Rav Zutra* did I skip a line? Thank you I skipped a
line. ואמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב *Va-amar Rav Zutra bar
Tuvia amar Rav* אבוקה כשניים *avuka ke-shnayim* so the same amora here's
just some random statements a torch counts as two people and a...
and the moon כשלשה like three people. You're not supposed to go
out at night alone, but if you have a torch that counts
like two people, and if it's a moonlit night, it counts as
three people. So and if you have street lamps that also counts.
So now it was said, so איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they raised
the question, אבוקה כשנים avuka kishnayim ובהדי דידיה, v'bahadi didey, when a
torch counts as two is it two plus you and you make
three או דילמא o dilma אבוקה כשנים avuka kishnayim לבר מיניה? l'var
miney? ובהדי דידיה v'bahadi didey means including you, you with the torch
is two או דילמא o dilma אבוקה כשנים avuka kishnayim לבר מיניה?
l'var miney? It's two in addition to you and you plus two
makes three. תא שמע coming here, וירח כשלשה, v'yarei'ach kishlosha, he says
the moon counts as three. אי אמרת בשלמא ei amart bishlama ובהדי
דידיה, v'bahadi didey, if it's including you, so it's two, it's three
with you counted, שפיר shappir I understand the idea of three. אלא
אי אמרת ella ei amart לבר מיניה l'var miney in addition to
you, so the moon counts as three and you're plus you that
makes four, ארבעה למה לי? arba'a lamma li? There's no הלכה halacha
four. There's only a הלכה halacha three. דאמר מר, d'amar mar, here's
where it matters how many people it is. לאחד נראה l'echad nir'a
it's an הלכה whatever anyway, if you go don't go out at
night alone because there are the מזיקין, mazikin, you know the evil
spirits. לאחד נראה ומזיק, l'echad nir'a u'mazik, it'll appear to you and
you'll be damaged, you'll be hurt by it. ולשנים נראה ואינו מזיק
u'lishnayim nir'a v'eino mazik if it's two people it'll appear but they
won't be hurt. ולשלשה אינו נראה כל עיקר u'lishlosha eino nir'a kol
ikkar for three it won't appear at all. So therefore there's no
there's no need for any more than three. אלא לאו שמע מינה
ella lav shma mina you see אבוקה כשנים avuka kishnayim ובהדי דידיה
v'bahadi didey it means two with you included and therefore and therefore
if you want not to see the שדים shedim at all, you
need to take the moon, a torch is not enough. שמע מינה.
shma mina. All right. So we'll just move on from that. Okay.
ואמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר רב חנא
בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא ואמרי לה אמר רבי יוחנן משום
רבי שמעון בן יוחי, v'amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvya amar Rav v'amrei
lah amar Rav Chana bar Bizna amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida v'amrei lah
amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, so the whole question
who says this. נוח לו לאדם שיפיל עצמו לתוך כבשן האש, no'ach
lo l'adam sheyapil atzmo l'toch kivshan ha'esh, this is a famous
גמרא, נוח לו לאדם שיפיל עצמו לתוך כבשן האש, no'ach lo l'adam
sheyapil atzmo l'toch kivshan ha'esh, better a person should cast themselves into
a fiery furnace ואל ילבין פני חבירו ברבים, v'al yalbin pnei chaveiro
barabbim, rather than cause the whitening like the blanching due to embarrassment
of their friend's face
in in public. מנלן מתמר, minalan miTamar, we learn it from תמר
Tamar שנאמר היא מוצאת she'ne'emar hi mutzet she was being taken out
and she didn't actually directly accuse יהודה, Yehuda, she figured I'll let
him choose if he wants to own up to it, I am
not going to embarrass him in public. It also was pretty strategic
of her because if she would have accused him he would have
denied it anyway. So okay, but anyway we are choosing to learn
from that how important it is not to embarrass people in public.
The reason we're quoting it here it's the same
מן דאמר, man d'amar, I'm going to have to ask for no
questions till we get to the end.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. הביאו לפניו שמן והדס. heviu lefanav shemen v'hadas.
Now we're back to the דרך הסעודה, derech hase'uda, the normal way
things would be brought out in the meal. You remember the washing
the hands, the בורא פרי הגפן. So apparently at the end of
the meal they would also bring out oil and myrtle. Oil maybe
to wash the hands, but it also becomes clear pretty later they're
also for the smell of the oil. They would both put it
on their body presumably and smell it. And the myrtle to smell,
the הדס hadas to smell. בית שמאי אומרים מברך על השמן ואחר
כך מברך על ההדס. Beit Shammai omrim mevarech al hashemen v'achar kach
mevarech al hahadas. First you make the ברכה on the oil then
you make it on the הדס. hadas. ובית הלל אומרים מברך על
ההדס ואחר כך מברך על השמן. u'Veit Hillel omrim mevarech al hahadas
v'achar kach mevarech al hashemen. First on the הדס hadas and then
on the oil. Not exactly clear what this debate is about. Reminds
us of the debate do you make בורא פרי הגפן first or
do you make you know מקדש השבת mekadesh hashabbat by קידוש, kiddush.
famous debate בית הלל בית שמאי. Beit Hillel Beit Shammai. But there
you know it's clear straight like הלכה about how did we structure
קידוש. Kiddush, Here it's hard to understand what's really at stake but
it's treating this as a real הלכה question, which ברכה comes first.
So let's take a look. אמר רבן גמליאל אני אכריע. amar Rabban
Gamliel ani achria. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says I'll decide. שמן זכינו
לריחו וזכינו לסיכתו. shemen zachinu l'reicho v'zachinu l'sichato. Oil is more important
than myrtle. Oil you both get nice smell from it and you
put it on your body. הדס לריחו זכינו לסיכתו לא זכינו. hadas
l'reicho zachinu l'sichato lo zachinu. Myrtle we only have benefit from its,
we're merited its smell not its putting it on our body. And
therefore it's more important, oil's more important, so you make oil first
like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כדברי המכריע. amar
Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'divrei hamachria. We rule like the one who cast
the deciding vote. Now normally, which is fascinating we rule like בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. It's also fascinating because normally מכריע machria is somebody
that finds a compromise position. This isn't a compromise position. He's just
saying בית שמאי's Beit Shammai position makes more sense. So let's see
where the גמרא continues. רב פפא איקלע לבי רב הונא בריה דרב
איקא. Rav Pappa ikla l'bei Rav Huna breih d'Rav Ika. So רב
פפא came to the house of רב הונא Rav Huna the son
of רב איקא. Rav Ika. אייתו לקמייהו שמן והדס. ayitu l'kamayehu shemen
v'hadas. They brought in front of them oil and הדס. hadas. שקל
רב פפא בריך אהדס ברישא. shakal Rav Pappa berich ahadas breisha. רב
פפא took the הדס hadas and made the first ברכה like בית
הלל. Beit Hillel. והדר בריך אשמן, v'hadar berich ashemen, then on the
oil. אמר ליה, amar leh, didn't he say לא סבר ליה מר
הלכה כדברי המכריע? lo savar leh mar halacha k'divrei hamachria? Don't you
hold we rule like the מכריע? machria? And and therefore we should
go like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who said אני אכריע ani achria
and go like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? אמר ליה, amar leh, הכי
אמר רבא. hachi amar Rava. Here's what רבא Rava says, הלכה כבית
הלל. halacha k'Veit Hillel. No we actually in this case, even though
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel sides with בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, we rule
like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you make on the הדס hadas first.
And then the גמרא comments ולא היא v'lo hi that really wasn't
true. רבא Rava never said that. אשתמוטי הוא דאשתמיט ליה, ishtamuti hu
d'ishtamit leh, he just was dodging it. The way רבא *Rava* said
it because he was embarrassed. We just read you're not supposed to
embarrass somebody in public anyway, he was caught that he made a
halachic mistake, so he said, oh רבא *Rava* says we go like
בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, so to get out of it, right, after
having run his mouth that he really was, he misrepresented הלכה *Halacha*
just to get out of that embarrassment. So there's a very ingenious
answer to this. I forget who says it, but I think it
might be the שלה *Shlah*. He says רבא *Rava* says in another
גמרא *Gemara* that when we say we rule like the מכריע *machria*,
the מכריע *machria* has to be, like I said before, a compromise
position, a middle position. The principle הלכה כדברי המכריע *Halacha ke-divrei ha-machria*
does not apply when it's just somebody siding with somebody else. So
in some way it's true, based on what רבא *Rava* said about
what it means הלכה כדברי המכריע *Halacha ke-divrei ha-machria*, the הלכה *Halacha*
would not be like בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* because רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel* is not a real מכריע *machria*. But he was just saying
רבא *Rava* says we go like בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, so that
was a slight misrepresentation. He never said we go like בית הלל
*Beis Hillel*, but based on רבא *Rava*'s teaching we would wind up
with that point. So it's a very ingenious answer. But anyway, simply
the גמרא *Gemara* is just saying, look, he just made it up
in order to get out of it.
Can you compromise if there're only two choices?
Well no, sometimes you can say in this case it's like you
and in that case it's like him, or like there's a middle
position, which whatever. That's when we normally say הלכה כדברי המכריע *Halacha
ke-divrei ha-machria*. This is not really a מכריע *machria*.
So when they do these questionings and one רב *Rav* does this
one way, one says, how come you didn't do this first and
the group instead of second, that's not humiliating the רב *Rav*?
Well, that maybe part of the question in the earlier context, but
in a case in which that's the whole discourse is that we're
all always talking about הלכה *Halacha* and it's always an acceptable sort
of dialogue. Okay, so we only have like two minutes, so we've
got a lot of גמרא *Gemara* to read, so let's hold off
on questions. תנו רבנן *Tano Rabbanan*, הביאו לפניהם שמן ויין *Hevi'u lifneihem
shemen ve-yayin*. Now you have to decide at the end of the
meal between oil and wine. בית שמאי אומרים *Beis Shammai omrim* אוחז
את השמן בימינו ואת היין בשמאלו *ochez es ha-shemen bi-yemino ve-es ha-yayin
bi-semolo*. Again, the oil comes first, you hold the oil in your
right hand and the wine in your left hand. מברך על השמן
והדר מברך על היין *mevarech al ha-shemen ve-hadar mevarech al ha-yayin*. First
you make the ברכה *bracha* on the oil, then on the wine.
בית הלל אומרים *Beis Hillel omrim* the opposite order, אוחז את היין
בימינו ואת השמן בשמאלו *ochez es ha-yayin bi-yemino ve-es ha-shemen bi-semolo*, the
wine in the right hand, the oil in the left hand. מברך
על היין והדר מברך על השמן *mevarech al ha-yayin ve-hadar mevarech al
ha-shemen*. And first the wine and then the oil. Again, not clear
exactly what that's all about. וטחו בראש השמש *ve-tacho be-rosh ha-shamash*, now
you've got oil on your hands, and this was like aromatic oil
because we saw you making ברכות *brachos* on it. What do you
do with this oil now that you've put it on your hands?
וטחו בראש השמש *ve-tacho be-rosh ha-shamash*, you sort of wipe your hand
on the head or on the hair of the שמש *shamash*. Okay,
so maybe he would like some oil as well, it's maybe nice
to him, he gets some nice oil. And the reason you're going
to do it, we're going to see, is because you're not supposed
to go out smelling too perfumed outside on the street. אם שמש
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham הוא *im shamash talmid chacham hu*, if the
שמש *shamash* is a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, a Torah scholar, doesn't
want to have this oil on his hair, טחו בכותל *tacho be-kosel*,
wipe your hand on the wall. Now, why is there this issue
of wiping your hand or the תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* doesn't want
it? מפני שגנאי לתלמיד חכם לצאת לשוק כשהוא מבושם *mipnei she-gnai le-talmid
chacham la-tzeis la-shuk ke-she-hu mevusam*. It is considered to be not fitting,
unseemly, for a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* to go out into the
marketplace, we will see, when he is perfumed. תנו רבנן *Tano Rabbanan*,
let's wrap this up, this is one more point till the end.
ששה דברים גנאי לו לתלמיד חכם *shishah devarim gnai lo le-talmid chacham*.
Six things are considered unfitting of a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*. אל
יצא כשהוא מבושם לשוק *al yeitzei ke-she-hu mevusam la-shuk*, do not go
out perfumed into the marketplace. ואל יצא יחידי בלילה *ve-al yeitzei yechidi
ba-laylah*, don't go out alone at night. No comments. ואל יצא במנעלים
המטולאים *ve-al yeitzei be-min'alaim ha-metulaim*, do not go out with shoes that
have patches on them. ואל יספר עם אשה בשוק Ve'al yesaper im
isha bashuk *ve-al yesaper im ishah ba-shuk*, do not speak to a
woman in the marketplace. ואל ישב בחבורה של עמי הארץ דרך הסיבה
*ve-al yeiseiv be-chaburah shel amei ha-aretz derech haseibah*, do not recline in
a group of the עמי הארץ *amei ha-aretz*, the unlearned. ואל יכנס
באחרונה לבית המדרש *ve-al yikanes ba-achronah le-vais ha-midrash*, don't be the last
guy into the בית המדרש *beis ha-midrash*. ויש אומרים אף לא יפסיע
פסיעה גסה Veyeish omrim af lo yafsia psia gassah *ve-yeish omrim af
lo yafsia pesiah gasah*, do not take a large step. ואל ילך
בקומה זקופה *ve-al yeileich be-kumah zekufah*, do not walk with an upright
stature, like an overly proud stature. אל יצא כשהוא מבושם *al yeitzei
ke-she-hu mevusam*. Now we're going to analyze it. אל יצא כשהוא מבושם
לשוק *al yeitzei ke-she-hu mevusam la-shuk*, do not go perfumed into the
marketplace. אמר חייא בר אבא אמר רבי Rebbe יוחנן *amar Chiya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan*: במקום שחשודים על משכב זכר *bi-mkom she-chashudan al
mishkav zachar*. It's a place where people are suspect of homosexual activity
and therefore, if you're walking around that way, you will be suspect
because that was how people would signal their availability, presumably. אמר רב
ששת *amar Rav Sheshes*: לא אמרן אלא בבגדו *lo amran ela be-begdo*.
That's only if it's on your clothes. אבל בגופו *aval be-gufo*, if
you want to put this nice oil on your body, זיעא מעברא
ליה *zei me-avra lei*, then the sweat will cause it to evaporate
and you don't have to worry that you'll be too smelly, it'll
also be a nice, do a good thing about covering over your
bad smells. אמר רב פפא *amar Rav Pappa*: ושערו כבגדו דמי *ve-saro
ki-vegdo dami*, your hair, like we talked before about the hair of
the תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, that's like your clothes, it'll still be
very smelly. ואמרי לה כגופו דמי *ve-amrei lei ke-gufo dami*, and others
say it's like your body, it'll get absorbed, it's not such a
problem.
That's the שמן *shemen*. ואל יצא יחידי בלילה *ve-al yeitzei yechidi ba-laylah*,
don't go out alone, משום חשדא *mishum cheshada*, because of suspicion. People
will think, why's he going? He's got some assignation, he's meeting some
woman in private. ולא אמרן אלא Velo amran ella דלא קביע ליה
עדנא *ve-lo amran ela de-lo kvia lei idna*. That's only if you
don't have any fixed time, like רש"י *Rashi* said, you're going to
an appointment, like... the בית מדרש Beis Medrash at night or you
know they know you're regular you learn with your רבי at night.
אבל קביעה ליה עדנא Aval kvia lei idna if you've got a
fixed time for doing something at night מידע ידעי דלענייניה קאזיל meidei
yadai dile'inyaneih ka'azil people know you're going to your appointment and it's
not a problem. ואל יצא במנעליים המטולאים Ve'al yetzei bemin'alayim hametula'im don't
go out with patched shoes, מסייע ליה לרבי חייא בר אבא דאמר
רבי חייא בר אבא msayei lei l'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba d'amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba גנאי הוא לתלמיד חכם שיצא במנעליים המטולאים gnai hu
l'talmid chacham sheyeitzei bemin'alayim hametula'im
pretty much the same thing, it is unfitting to go out for
a תלמיד חכם to go out with patched shoes. איני? Eini? Is
that true? והא רבי חייא בר אבא נפיק! Veha Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba nafik! But the רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
himself went out! So אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן amar Mar
Zutra brei d'Rav Nachman בטלאי על גב טלאי. betlai al gav tlai.
Now the problem is when your patches have patches.
Normally a patch is alright, everybody got a patch on their shoes,
with patches on your patches that's the problem. ולא אמרן אלא on
your shoes, בפנתא, befanta, that's only like on the main part of
the shoe, אבל בגלדא, aval begilda, which is like the heel, לית
לן בה lais lan bah that's not a problem, the sole, the
heel, that's not a problem, that was more acceptable. ובפנתא לא אמרן
אלא באורחא, Ubefanta lo amran ella be'orcha, even that is only a
problem when you're going out outside, אבל בביתא aval beveisa just to
wear in your house, לית לן בה lais lan bah also not
a problem. ולא אמרן אלא בימות החמה Velo amran ella biyemos hachamah
and it was a problem, it's only a problem in the summer,
אבל בימות הגשמים aval biyemos hageshamim in the rain season, לית לן
בה lais lan bah it's not a problem either because you want
to wear not so nice shoes or the mud will cover them.
Okay. ואל יספר עם אשה בשוק don't talk to a woman in
the marketplace. אמר רב חסדא אפילו היא אשתו Amar Rav Chisda afilu
hi ishto even your wife. It was not seen as, you know,
proper conventionally. תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi we've taught similarly, אפילו
אשתו afilu ishto even your wife, ואפילו בתו ואפילו אחותו ve'afilu bito
ve'afilu achoto even your daughter even your sister, לפי שאין הכל בקיאין
בקרובותיו lefi she'ein hakol b'ki'in bikrovosav nobody, not everybody knows who your
relatives are. So they'll think you're talking to a strange woman. Who
is that woman I saw you with? And they'll have all their
very suspicions. So therefore you don't want people to have these suspicions.
Obviously reflects very different societal norms. And it's interesting to think by
the way that even people that try to sort of keep and
say that we don't make changes based on societal norms and everything
is exactly the way it is in גמרא, I wonder how many
חרדים Charedim don't talk to their wives in public. Maybe there are,
I'm sure there are some. Okay. Anyway. ואל יסב בחבורה של עם
הארץ Ve'al yeiseiv bachaburah shel am ha'aretz
don't recline with with the commoners. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דלמא אתי
לאמשוכי בתרייהו Dilma asi l'amshuchei basraihu because you start hanging out with
people, you'll start following their ways. ואל יכנס אחרון לבית המדרש Ve'al
yikanes acharon l'Beis Medrash don't be the last guy into the בית
מדרש משום דקרו ליה פושע mishum d'karu lei poshea
because they'll call you negligent, you're lazy. Somebody's got to be last,
shouldn't be you. ויש אומרים אף לא יפסיע פסיעה גסה psia gassah
do not take a big step, דאמר מר פסיעה גסה נוטלת אחד
מחמש מאות ממאור עיניו של אדם. d'amar mar psia gassah noseles echad
mechamesh me'os mima'or einav shel adam. A big step makes you lose
one-fifth, 1/500th of your eyesight. So מאי תקנתיה? Mai takantei? So right,
it's more of a health thing than anything else. What how do
you fix it? להדרי בקידושא דבי שמשי. lehadrei bekidusha d'bei shimshi. If
you drink the wine of קידוש, Kiddush that reverses it. So which
is interesting because taking a פסיעה גסה psia gassah. on שבת Shabbos
is like running on שבת, Shabbos, so maybe the wine of קידוש
is a reversal for the idea of פסיעה גסה. Anyway. ואל יהלך
בקומה זקופה Ve'al yehalech b'komah zkufah do
not go with an upright stature, דאמר מר המהלך בקומה זקופה d'amar
mar hamahalech b'komah zkufah again it doesn't mean don't slouch, but don't
do it in an overly haughty bearing because if somebody goes in
an overly upright bearing, אפילו ארבע אמות afilu arba amos even if
you just walk four אמות, amos, כאילו דוחק רגלי השכינה ke'ilu dochek
raglei haShechinah it's like you're pushing God's legs away, דכתיב מלא כל
הארץ כבודו deksiv m'lo chol ha'aretz kvodo the whole land is filled
with God's glory and you are saying I'm the important one here,
not God. All right, to be continued tomorrow.